Guide to the Edward Jenner Papers, 1800-1822 and undated RL.11401
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters
  - Edward Jenner (Berkeley, Gloucestershire) to [William Davies] (no place), 1818 November 6; 1 leaf; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner comments on the rain, then suggests the trade of a tongue for a sparerib.He promises to send books as soon as young Willy learns to read.
  - Edward Jenner (no place) to William [Davies?] (no place), 1818 December 4; 1 leaf; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner states that he is sorry to learn William has been ill, then invites him to dine on venison that afternoon.
  - Edward Jenner (Berkeley, Gloucestershire) to Nigel Kingscote (Worcester, England), 1819 December 27; 1 leaf; 3 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner rejoices in the health of his friend and his friend's wife. He then discusses the recent insurrection and the existing laws regarding it. In a postscript he seeks a position in "one of the public offices" for T. Marklove. Contains an additional address in red ink
  - Edward Jenner (no place) to William [Davies?] (no place), 1819; 1 leaf; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner requests Davies' presence in order to discuss the potential lending of money to Mrs. Marklove, as executor of the Marklove estate. The date has been provided in red ink, along with an additional note by Davies that Jenner ultimately refused to lend the money
  - Edward Jenner (Berkeley, Gloucestershire) to "My Dear Sir" (no place), 1820 April 24; 1 leaf; 2 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner writes that at this time of year he finds children often have herpetic blotches that make them unsuitable for vaccination. He notes that he did manage to vaccinate two children, who will be ready to meet the correspondent's purposes later in the week. Additional note in another hand identifying the letter as Jenner's. Transcription available.
  - Edward Jenner (Berkeley, Gloucestershire) to "My Lord" (no place), 1821 March 26; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 32 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner writes to return an oath he has signed, hoping that it has been executed properly. He would have taken the oath in person if his health permitted it. Accompanied by the oath, sworn and signed, consequent to his appointment to the place of Physician Extraordinary to His Majesty, George IV, on March 26, 1821.
  - Edward Jenner (Berkeley, Gloucestershire) to William [Davies?] (no place), 1821 August 1; 1 leaf; 2 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner writes concerning illness suffered by William's son and their governess.
  - Edward Jenner (Berkeley, Gloucestershire) to Charles [Jenner] (no place), 1821 August 28; 1 leaf; 3 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner discusses a printing job on vaccinations. He doesn't like the flourishes Fosbrooks has added, "but should it lessen human misery I shall be happy in having sent it out." It requires an introduction by Charles. He then discusses his financial arrangements with F--, along with family members. Transcription available.
  - Edward Jenner (Berkeley, Gloucestershire) to Charles [Jenner] (no place), 1821 December 27; 2 Leaves; 4 pages; 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner promises to collect geological specimens for Charles to examine. He also comments on a written piece being printed to which he has provided corrections. Two copies. The second version is missing some of the original text and has a biographical sketch pasted to it.
  - Edward Jenner (Berkeley, Gloucestershire) to Rev. Dr. Davies (Rockhampton, England), 1822 September 2; 1 leaf; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner writes with instructions regarding a discussion of a property title dispute he has with Mrs. Hickes.
  - Edward Jenner (Cheltenham, England) to William [Davies?] (no place), 1822; 1 leaf; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner requests a meeting to discuss his Berkeley farms. Date has been added in red ink
  - Edward Jenner (Cheltenham, England) to Thomas Paytherns (London, England), October 1; 1 leaf; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner writes of a house he has rented, mentions a discussion with a printer, and offers his note on election day.
  - Edward Jenner (Berkeley, Gloucestershire) to William [Davies?] (no place), November 31; 1 leaf; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner mentions the health of two patients, one of whom has a fever.
  - Edward Jenner (no place) to Rev. William Davies (Eastington, Gloucestershire), June 7; 1 leaf; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner wishes he could have no further contact with Robert Clarke, then asks Davies to keep the cash he has since Jenner has no need of it. He mentions a plan to return to Berkeley.
  - Edward Jenner (Cheltenham, England) to Rev. William Davies (Eastington, Gloucestershire), November 6; 1 leaf; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner outlines his plan to print copies of "scraps" to be given away. He adds that "Fosbrooke has been here" and is in good spirits, although he adds "The immense quantity of snuff that is flowing up his Nostrils in one continued stream, must finally do him irreparable injury." He directs Davies to pay Larne a sum of 80 pounds or more.
  - Edward Jenner (Cheltenham, England) to Rev. William Davies (Eastington, Gloucestershire), no date; 1 leaf; 2 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner lists his advocates (in regard to vaccination?), then discusses matters on the farm, including picking cherries, an auction (for grain?), and, in a postscript, the preparation of one of his houses for residents.He wishes the Rockhampton surgeon to contact him and provide updates on veterinary proceedings.
  - Edward Jenner (no place) to Rev. William Davies (Rockhampton, England), no date; 1 leaf; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner discusses the murder of Mr. Perceval, brother of Lord Arden. He requests copies of the Gibraltar Book.
  - Edward Jenner (no place) to William [Davies?] (no place), no date; 1 leaf; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner discusses the matter of the Jenkins' servant, and whether she should be prosecuted.
  - Edward Jenner (no place) to Miss L. Fust (Hill Court), no date; 1 leaf; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner requests the living at Hill Court to be given to his nephew, Rev. G. Jenner. Marked "a copy"
  - Edward Jenner (no place) to Dr. Pemberton (no place), no date; 1 leaf; 1 page; 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Jenner sends a note regarding "the most common obstruction to the correct action of the vaccine virus, both locally and constitutionally."
- Miscellaneous papers (Box 1, Folder 3)
  There are a few miscellaneous papers, including poems, a prescription and a recipe, and a receipt for the Royal Jennerian Society.
- Prescriptions (Volume 1)
  There are four holograph prescriptions and two recipes (1807-1821), four with initials "E.J.," mounted and bound in a volume with an engraved portrait of Jenner.
- Diary (Volume 2)
  Collection also includes a manuscript diary (188 pages) maintained by Jenner in 1811 and the Fall of 1812, primarily containing notes on his patients and their treatments for various illnesses, from syphilis to gout to heart ailments (including prescriptions) along with records of many vaccinations. There is a note of receipt of a letter (1812 Sept 12) from Dr. Alex Crichton stating that vaccination flourished throughout the Russian Empire. Also contains reports on the dissection of organs from a cow, horse, and sheep, along with two sets of notations regarding diabetes, and one on "pulmonary affections." There are occasional notes with weather observations, recipes, lists of letters written, patient charges or payments, and a few comments on his house repairs using stucco. At the end of the volume are a number of poems and epigrams.